Hello, and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrdan.
And today we're going to be looking
at Le Chatelier's principle.
Now, what this is all about is that
whenever we have a reversible reaction,
meaning we have a forward and the
reverse, when they are at equilibrium,
it is possible to disturb that
equilibrium, to apply a stress to it,
meaning that the reaction can shift.
It can either get pushed towards
the forward or towards the reverse.
And it's all based on different
conditions we apply to the reaction.
So the actual official definition of
this is that whenever you place an
external stressor on a reaction at
equilibrium, it has to respond to it.
So like one example to this is, you
know, if you, if you're in your classroom
and your teacher tells you, Hey, you
have a test next, next class, then all
of a sudden your heart starts racing.
That's like, Oh no, you know,
I got to start studying.
I got to prepare for this.
There's all the, all this different things
that start racing through your brain.
That's a stress, right?
And your body's going to respond
by telling you to study and
prepare and do and respond to that.
So whenever the system responds within
a chemical reaction, the rate of the
forward or the reverse reaction changes
either to increase or decrease in
order to try to relieve that stress.
So we'll be talking about it
shifting left, right, in terms of.
The reverse and the forward reaction.
So now let's some more examples of
like exactly where do we see this?
This is all over the
place in everyday life.
Um, there are a lot of different
systems that are in place.
To actually work off the
ideas behind equilibrium.
One of the most common ones
is lines at theme parks.
So if you've ever gone to Disneyland,
Disney hires people to actually make
different models that are pretty much
based off equilibrium problems to
how to try to shift the population
around the park in order to give you
the most fun filled experience and
the happiest experience possible.
And this happens in many theme parks.
So one of the things that you see
the second you walk into the park is
essentially an entire list of all the
queue times, how to get onto every ride.
And usually the thing that you're
looking for is you're always looking
for what's the most exciting ride.
And then also what is
the shortest wait times.
And those times are being
shown to you on purpose.
So that way.
It spreads the population around the
park into different areas, right?
It might say it's five
minutes to get onto.
Let's say splash mountain.
The second you get there, you see like,
Oh, all of a sudden it's 15 minutes.
Well, that's because people are trickling
over that reaction essentially got
shifted in that direction, right?
There was a stress on the park and it got
shifted to a different area of the park.
So that's one way to try to potentially
make the reactions go faster.
So that way no one's
waiting in lines too much.
They keep updating those times.
To make it faster and faster and
to change the different places.
Um, another really big example
is actually with traffic too.
If you ever try to plug in a
destination on your GPS, sometimes
it might give you your normal route,
but it might say, hey, this route
is going to be 5 minutes faster.
GPS's are also programmed to try
to relieve the stress on streets.
So that way you're not waiting
in 45 minute traffic if you
want to go one direction.
First, let's say another direction, right?
Especially if you like, um, being
that myself, I was living in LA
for a really long time, this was a
really common thing you would do.
You'd either take the highways
or the surface streets to try to
avoid all the different kind of
chaotic messes that might occur.
So there are different ways
to try to avoid and try to.
shift the whole idea of equilibrium
because this is a dynamic process.
So it's always changing constantly
whenever we're looking at equilibrium.
So we're going to be looking at
all the different factors in this
video and trying to understand them
and going through many different
examples on how to break them down.
All right, let's go take a look at
this and I hope that this helps you
and thank you so much for listening.
Let's continue to look
at the next part with
the different factors.
What we're going to be looking at is
essentially in a way we're going to
be poking the reaction with a stick
and asking it, Hey, can you go do
something right now as a reaction?
So that's what Le Chatelier's
principle was all about.
He essentially determined like,
Hey, that when he was noticing
with chemical reactions that
whenever we change something.
The system would respond, and
mainly it boiled down to about five
different major factors that do do
something to the chemical reaction.
It's mainly with concentration, so how
much, how many moles of your reactant
or product are in the system, how hot
or cold is it, the pressure and volume,
so how big or small the container is.
And then when you add a catalyst or an
enzyme to the mixture, that's going to
essentially spawn and change as well.
So that's what we're going to be
looking at and trying to determine
how do each one of these affect these
different changes and how can we
exactly shift this reaction one way or
another when we are looking at these.
So let's take a look.
The first one is all changing the
concentration in the reaction,
meaning that we're going to be
essentially kind of lifting the
reaction one way versus another.
So when we are looking at this, the
way that we got to kind of think
about it is similar to scales, but in
terms of if we're going to be kind of
like lifting one side over another.
So let's say if I have the first
one here and I ask you, what
happens if I increase a, all right,
well, a is one of our reactants.
You see it as it's in pink
on the left hand side.
So what if I increase that?
Well, the whole idea is if all of a sudden
I start increasing a, it's going to lead
it to more collisions with everything
around it, meaning you have a lot of
a, so essentially the probability of it
finding B increases pretty dramatically.
So if we increase this side, one
way for you to kind of look at
this reaction is, is almost as if
you're going to be Uh, tipping it
in one direction versus another.
So it's getting raised by it going
upwards and it's going to be tipped.
The scales tip.
So when that happens, well, what
direction will that reaction go?
Because these increased collisions are
all running into each other, the reaction
is going to push forward and heavily.
It's going to try to.
Relieve that stress by making more
products because the goal is for the
rates to be equal So once all of a
sudden these all these reactants are
here It's making it so there's going
to be a lot of reaction occurring
forward wise So eventually the
scales can try to tip back into place
is what we're going to be seeing.
So in this case, the reaction
will shift right because of that
stress that's placed on the system.
When you have extra A particles, they
will collide with B to make C and D.
So over time, what you're going to see
is that those scales that are like this,
they'll start to slowly come back to
being even after the reaction occurs.
So in this case, the
reaction would shift right.
Let's look at another
example of concentration.
Now what would happen if I decreased
the concentration of B instead?
So if I were to go through this particular
reaction and I were to decrease it,
well, it's gonna be the same kind of
concept with the, the reverse, right?
The system's going to respond.
It's gonna be like, oh my God,
where do all the beam molecules go?
It's going to freak out a little
bit, and it's gonna try to
produce more to respond to this.
So when we start to decrease that one
reaction, it's gonna be as if the entire
system is going to try to tip itself.
in the direction to create more.
So in this case, what are we going to see
is that the reverse reaction is going to
happen very heavily to try to shift it
in the direction to compensate for that.
Um, when all of a sudden there's,
there's less B in the system, that
means the probability for C and D
to collide with each other is going
to increase a lot as a result.
So the reaction will shift left when
that reaction reactant is removed.
The system will compensate
by creating more reactants.
So that means the reverse reactant will
increase until equilibrium is restored.
Let's go on to another.
So another, so another reaction
is, well, what would happen if
I remove C as soon as it forms?
Right?
So immediately what would exactly happen?
So if I keep trying to
remove C from the reaction.
Once again, the system
is going to compensate.
So if I keep removing that, the reaction
essentially will want to go forward
as a result to make more C, right?
So as we, as we remove it,
it wants to replace it.
Now the whole idea here
is, well, why is that?
Is because all these atoms that are
in a container in the solution or in
the gas phase, They're going to be
colliding with everything around them.
So if they can't find a C atom to hit.
It's more likely that A and B will
collide with each other, so it will shift
that reaction forward to compensate.
So if something is decreasing,
the reaction is going to
end up shifting towards it.
And if something is increasing, it's
going to end up shifting away from it.
So that's going to be one of the
ideas that we're seeing here.
Let's go on to another example.
So let's say if I wanted to look at
an actual real chemical reaction.
So right here, I have iron
thiocyanate and what's happening
is it's dissociating in solution.
So what would happen if I add a common
ion of another compound into the
solution, meaning that if you see the
SCN is part of the reactants and the
products, just one part of it is bound.
So what would occur if I, let's say, if I
add N a SCN into the mixture here, Well,
what would end up occurring as a result?
Well, we got to think, well, what
would happen if this molecule
were to go into solution?
Well, this is what has to do
with your solubility rules.
So if we were to add this guy, it's
going to essentially dissociate
into its different pieces, right?
You'd have NA plus and then you'd
also have SCN minus would be the other
component that would be made in solution.
So you're going to have
these two different pieces.
So if we are creating a bunch of SCN,
well, in that case, if we look at our
original reaction, this side is going
to be increasing by a lot, right?
It's because we're making
more of those ions.
So how is the system going to
respond by the right hand increasing?
Because of that going up, it's going
to want to shift the reaction in the
reverse direction or to the left in
order to make more reactant, right?
So if you add a common ion, it depends
on like, what are the different products,
but being that we're going to make
more SCN, it's going to increase SCN
shifting the reaction to the left.
So just to kind of wrap up concentration,
one way that we can really look
at that, if you take a substance
the reaction shifts towards the
substance, meaning if you take it away.
Um, if you add a substance, the
reaction shifts away from the substance.
So try to remember the T's and the A's.
So if you take, it goes towards,
and if you add, it goes away
is one way to look at it.
So in this situation, We added
SCN and it moved away from that
in the original reaction, right?
It moved away from it.
So add away take towards this
one way to kind of remember it.
I also like to think of it
trying to as a shifting part.
So in this case, right, we added SCN.
So it's like we're trying to tip
the reaction in this direction.
So we're going to be
making a lot more FFCN.
It's like, Tipping the balances,
so it's getting weighed in one
direction versus another is
another way to look at that too.
Let's go into our next factor.
So with temperature, the whole idea
here is that it's going to actually
be very similar to concentration.
We can actually treat
it in a similar respect.
But before we do that, we have to remember
the different labels for temperature
when it came to a chemical reaction.
Well, the first thing was the word
endothermic and exothermic, right?
Endothermic meant that
heat is being absorbed.
And the heat is a reactant when
you label it in the problem,
exothermic heat is a product, right?
And you put it as a product in that
reaction to, there were different
signs behind these as well.
So if you remember, uh, whenever it
was endothermic, it was positive.
Whenever it was exothermic,
it was negative.
So that's really important.
And then the life last thing is whenever
energy, how was it measured, right?
It was always in kilojoules.
And then it was shown as delta
H or enthalpy, which were always
reflected the amount of heat that
was absorbed or released in a
reaction at a constant pressure.
So that's one thing that
we got to keep in mind too.
So let's say if I were to be given
a chemical reaction similar to the
one before, or if A plus 2B makes
C plus D, and I say delta H is
equal to negative 250 kilojoules.
Well, when we're writing this,
you got to kind of recognize,
well, is it exo or is it endo?
What exactly are we doing?
Cause you gotta be able, you
gotta write it in the reaction.
And this is what I meant that you
can kind, you can treat it like
concentration because essentially if
you're increasing or decreasing it,
it's going to kind of push the reaction.
in a very similar manner.
So let's say if I kind of rewrote
this, right, it's exothermic.
So that means that energy is a product.
So we're going to write
that on the right hand side.
So the reason I could say it's XO
is because it's negative 250, right?
So that tells you product.
So in this case, if I increased
more energy, so increasing heat,
Well, that means you're going to be
raising this side up as a result,
so it's going to get a lot hotter.
So when that's getting hotter, what
is it going to be essentially doing?
Well, we're going to be shifting
that reaction to respond to that.
It's going to shift the reaction in
the other direction, just like how
we did earlier with concentration.
We're going to raise that side up.
So that way it's going to shift
in the, uh, and essentially
in the other direction, right?
So when we shift that, so
if that increases, we are
going to shift away from it.
So we will do that.
So add away.
So we add heat.
We're going to shift away from heat.
All right.
So that's what will happen there.
Now, what if I wanted to
decrease that temperature?
Well, it's going to be
generally the same idea, right?
If I decrease that temperature, um, and
we want the system to get a lot colder
as a result, well, we can essentially say
that, well, the reaction is super cold.
So it's going to want to respond to that.
by it wanting to go in
the opposite direction.
So if we go really cold with our
heat, it's going to respond and want
to go forward to generate more heat.
It's going to, once we take away a
substance, it's going to want to go
towards that substance is the whole idea.
So that's how we can look at temperature.
Let's look at another though.
Sometimes when it comes to reactions,
you might not be given an actual
numerical value and I'll just say, Hey,
there's heat involved in this problem.
So with this one, it says, what will
happen if you increase the temperature?
So we'd still treat it as XR endothermic.
So that's your responsibility
to kind of remember that trend.
So if it's on the left hand side, that
meant that it's absorbing heat, that's
endothermic is how we can look at that.
So if I want to increase that heat,
well, we are going to be adding heat.
So what's it going to do?
It's going to shift away from it.
So that means it's going to
shift to the right hand side to
generate more product in this case.
Now if we had the opposite here Where
let's say if I wanted to decrease
that, well, how is the system
going to respond by decreasing?
So I'm going to make
this really, really cold.
Well, that means that the system's
going to want to generate to
try to leave that equilibrium.
So it's going to shift towards
the heat direction, right?
If you take it away, it's going to shift.
towards that substance.
Let's take a look at our next factor.
Pressure change.
When it comes to pressure, these different
changes all have to do with gases.
So when we talk about pressure and
volume, we're talking about different
gas molecules because essentially
the size of their container does
affect how they react because gas
particles are very, very far apart.
So if a container is really
small, then the likelihood of them
colliding with each other increases.
So it's all about how big or how
small that container is, which will
increase or decrease the pressure.
So if I have a container
with a bunch of gases in it.
The reaction is going to
shift to reduce pressure.
Now, how can it do that?
Well, it's all about the
number of moles of gas.
So if I am to look at this, uh, particular
reaction, you can count the coefficients.
So if you see the reactants, right?
So two A plus b, I have two A
molecules and I have one B molecule.
So that means you have a total of
three reactants on the left hand side.
And then if you look at the right
hand side, I have on my products,
I have one C and then one D.
So that means you have
a total of two products.
So that means depending on how the
system responds, we'll essentially
try to alleviate that pressure.
So let's say if I increase the
pressure a lot, what it's going
to do, it's going to want to have
less moles of gas present to make.
It will, the pressure will go down
if there's a very, very low pressure.
Well, then it's going to try to fill that
void by going in the opposite direction.
And it's also all about what are
the probability of collisions
occurring to if you have, let's
say, a really small container.
That means a very, very high pressure.
Well, the likelihood likelihood Of
the three moles of reactants running
into each other increases by a lot.
So that's another reason why
it shifts in one direction.
Is what's the size of the container?
Who are you likely to run
into for a reaction to happen?
Right?
You have to, A has to run into
B for that reaction to happen.
C has to run into D for
that reaction to happen.
It's all about what is the probability
of the collisions occurring.
So if we were to look at this
one, what would happen if the
pressure were to decrease?
Well, if you remember from before
where we have three moles of gas on
the left, two moles on the right.
So it's going to try to
shift to compensate for this.
So if the pressure is really, really low,
it's going to want to bring it back up.
So it's going to want to
create more moles of gas.
So when that happens.
We're going to be shifting the
reaction to the left in order
to compensate for that, right?
It's going to want to create
more gas molecules, uh, in,
in, as a result of this.
Another reason to is being at
this container, right there.
It's going to be really big when it
has a low pressure, the likelihood
of the that number of moles running
into each other decreases as a result.
It actually becomes harder.
It's more likely that 2 products
will find each other, hit each other.
then it would be for three things to
hit each other all at the same time.
It's a little rarer.
So it's all about trying to figure out
how can you try to understand, see it.
But I think the easiest way is a, the
less moles going to shift towards more.
I think it's easy way to look at it.
All right.
Now what happens if the moles
were equal on both sides?
So I rewrote the equation.
So we have a new one.
So it's just a plus B is C, C plus D.
What would happen?
Well, if both are the same and let's
say increase or decrease pressure.
then it's not going to favor
one direction or the other.
So even if you, uh, increase
or decrease the pressure, there
won't be any change to it.
It's not going to matter.
It's going to still be at equilibrium,
even if you're making them really close
together or really far apart, because
there's no favoritism on one side or
the other, there will be no change.
Um, so, and that's going
to be kind of one thing.
Now, what if I added
another gas to the mixture?
Let's say it was something that's inert,
like something that would increase
the pressure Um, to the mixture.
Would that matter in that case?
Now, what being that is
not a part of the reaction.
Um, if it's actually also not going to
have a change that's going to occur in the
reaction, because it's not a part of it.
So you, it's essentially affecting
both sides equally equally.
So if we were to add something to
as a, almost like a, as a buffer in
this case, where it's just this big
gas, it's all surrounding everything.
Once again, it's going to be no change.
It has to be a common gas or a
common ion to have an effect.
Before we actually look at trying to
understand volume, believe it or not,
volume and pressure are actually very
intimately related to each other.
So if you remember as pressure increases,
volume decreases and vice versa, they
are an inverse relationship with one
another due to Boyle's law from gas laws.
So one thing about these containers that
if I, let's say, have a container of
gas and it's inside of a piston, Right.
And it, what this thing is describing is
the reaction above where I have hydrogen
combining with nitrogen to make ammonia.
Now, if this, if this container is at a
full size and I want to make it smaller,
where I push all the molecules together,
Notice how close everything is together.
So the likelihood of things
reacting can increase immensely.
So if I increase that, well, what
direction would the reaction likely shift?
So if we kind of look at the
total number of moles here, right?
I have four moles of gas.
on the left hand side, and then they
have two moles of gas on the right.
So meaning that if our pressure
goes up, it's going to want
to relieve that pressure.
So which direction is it
going to push the reaction?
Well, it's going to push it
forward to make less molecules.
And the way that we can see that if we
go from container B to container C, which
is right here, right next to me, notice
how essentially the molecules are a
little bit farther apart compared to B.
And that's because we have less molecules
because we made more ammonia as a result.
We shifted from going from just nitrogens
and hydrogens, like we see over here and
they're all really close together, they're
going to be bouncing all over the walls.
And it's going to create more reactions
to help relieve that pressure to mean
get back to equilibrium as a result.
So that's one thing that we can see.
The goal is to relieve stress
by essentially creating
less molecules in the space.
Thanks.
So if we increase pressure, it's
going to shift towards less moles.
If we decrease pressure, it's going to
want to go towards more moles as a result.
Um, so now let's go look at volume, which
is going to be very similar to this.
So the good news is that when
you change volume of a guess in a
system, it's actually going to have
the exact same effect as pressure.
Um, but you have to try to remember
that they are an inverse relationship.
So you do got to keep in mind that,
uh, as like pressure increases,
volume is going to decrease.
So you have to kind of remember those
little relationships that are here, right?
As one goes up, the other
one's going to go down.
So once again, though, the change
is determined by the number of
moles, um, when we have this.
And it's important to also realize
that, well, what would happen if you
have the same moles on each side?
Well, it's going to once again
be no change like before.
Um, and kind of going up to the
problem we had earlier, right?
That if you can see here, well, when
pressure increase, volume also decrease.
You can see how much smaller
the space is within this piston.
And it forced it forward.
So it's the same relationship that's
here, but you got to keep in mind
that when volume decreases, it's
going to shift it towards more moles.
And when volume increases, it will shift
it towards, um, less moles in our, I
think I might've said that backwards,
but essentially when you have the volume
decrease, it's going to shift it to
less moles and the volume increase,
it's going to go towards more moles.
So same idea as pressure.
All right.
So that's one way to kind of
keep, keep that in mind when
you're looking at it, it's going
to be the same idea as pressure.
Okay.
All right.
So let's take a look at our last one.
Catalysts and enzymes are one of
the most fundamental principles
around biology because essentially
what keeps us metabolically
functioning allows us to exist.
So equilibrium is a big part of how our
body actually functions and works because
it describes exactly how the chemical
reactions within those systems work.
So if I have a catalyst, what it does,
it speeds up the rate of the reaction.
by increasing the amount of collisions.
So it's going to cause
things to occur faster.
Now, when we have, let's say an enzyme,
the whole idea is when we have a reaction,
essentially, there is an activation energy
barrier for the reaction to go over in
order for the reaction to happen, right?
On the left hand side, we have
our reactants and on the right
hand side, we have our products.
So that big hump or that
big hill is your barrier.
So what essentially the enzyme is
trying to do is Hey, can we go around
the mountain or find an alternate
path in order to make that a reality?
So when we add an enzyme, usually it's
like going around the side of the mountain
in order to make this easier to occur.
It's less energy that is required.
Now the thing about this though, is
you kind of noted, you got to think
that, oh, it's not only about going
over the hill from one direction.
And yeah, There's people that
want to come from the harder
side to the strenuous side.
So both sides are
technically easier to cross.
So that means both the forward and
the reverse reaction are easier.
So as a result, that means that it
does not have an effect on equilibrium.
Overall, the whole reaction is just
faster regardless of the direction.
So which is kind of nice is that you don't
have to try to predict left or right.
It's not going to have an effect.
There are a couple important
things to mention about catalysts.
So the first thing is they
are not reactants, they
just speed up the reaction.
And generally they're not consumed or
destroyed in the reaction when it occurs
with the substrate they are bonding
to or the reactant they're bonding to.
Um, they are just essentially, uh,
assisting the reaction to happen.
They're kind of being like the crane arms
and the tools to help make these things
actually get there a little bit faster.
So the whole idea is that they
provide an alternate pathway.
So the way that I like to look at it is
like, if you kind of go, let's say down
a trail, And there's a sign there that
tells you all these different routes, and
many of them might lead to the same exact
spot, but there's different ways for you
to get there, different scenic routes
for you to take for you to get there.
So, one way that I like to always look
at it is, let's say if I were to look,
go on two different trails, well, when
you are hiking, well, how could you,
how could you get over the mountain top?
There are different routes.
Like, you could essentially go up this
and maybe you could go all the way up
to the very, very top of the mountain.
And then go over the backside
to get to the other part.
That's one way to do it.
Right?
I'm sure it'd be a really beautiful hike.
It's going to be really hard, but
there's one way to go around it.
The other way is, let's say if you're
not interested in going, you don't
want to go up over the mountain.
You just want to get to the other side.
And that's the goal.
Well, maybe you could just go up the
pass, which is a little bit easier, or
maybe you could even go all the way around
it and go through the valley as well.
There are different routes.
That's that's what enzymes do.
They offer different possibilities
to get around that peak, right?
Do you want to go over the mountain
or do you just want to just enjoy
a hike and go around and have
a little bit of an easier time?
It's about trying to lower
that activation energy barrier.
Whereas this guy all the way up here,
that's your activation energy barrier.
That's a really huge
peak to try to conquer.
So it provides an alternate path.
So that way the system will reach
equilibrium faster is the entire idea.
So that's the last part of
Le Chatelier's principle.
So as you could see, this was a
lot of different concepts, that
different factors that we could see.
So let's go back to them real quick.
As you can see, there was four
major factors that actually
had an effect on equilibrium.
catalyst and enzymes didn't.
So it really comes down to knowing
how these four play a role.
How essentially if I poke that
reaction with a stick, what
is exactly going to happen?
So with concentration and temperature,
they are very similar, right?
If you, if you add, uh, add
something to the reaction, it's
going to shift away from it.
And if you take it away, it's going
to shift towards that substance.
With pressure and volume, they
have to do with the number of, the
coefficients, right, so the number
of moles that are in a reaction.
So if you want to increase pressure
or decrease the volume, it's
going to shift towards less moles.
If you, uh, decrease the pressure,
increase the volume, it's going
to shift towards more moles.
So it's all about which
relationship do you have?
All right.
So, and then, and then with enzymes, it
did not have an effect on equilibrium.
So this has been my video on
Le Chatelier's principles.
So this is a broad overview of everything.
I hope that this video helped
a little bit understand it.
And if it didn't let me know, let me
hear, uh, tell me in the comments,
if you have questions or message me
outside of class and tell me all about
it or reach out to me via email or
message a message me and ask for help.
Okay.
I hope to see you all later, and thank
you so much for listening, and if this
is your first time here, please hit
that like and subscribe button and
keep supporting the channel to help
more students just like yourself.
Alright, this has been Dr.
Dan, and thank you so much for being here.
Bye now.